so this is angaya book of fours Su
number 162 um because there are four kinds of
162 um because there are four kinds of
practice what four unpleasant practice
with low Insight unpleasant practice
with swift Insight Pleasant practice
with slow insight and pleasant practice
practice with swift insight and what's
the unpleasant practice with slow
Insight it's when someone is by nature
acutely given to passion and often
experiences the pain and displeasure
born of passion they by Nature acutely
given to aversion and often experience
the pain and displeasure born of
aversion thereby nature acutely given to
muddled often translated as
delusion and often experience the pain
and displeasure born of
muddled these five faculties manifest in
them weak
Faith effort recollection composure and
understanding because of this they only
slowly come into proximity of the
destruction of the influxes this is
called the unpleasant practice with slow
slow insight and what's the unpleasant
practice with swift
Insight um so it's the same in terms of
being predisposed to to defilements more
strongly uh but then the five faculties
manifest in the strongly because of this
they swiftly come into proximity of the
destruction of the influxes this is
called the unpleasant practice with
swift insight and so what's the pleasant
insight and so what's the pleasant
practice with slow Insight it's when
someone is by nature not acutely given
to passion and doesn't often experience
the pain and displeasure born of passion
they're by Nature not acutely given to
aversion and don't often experience the
pain in this pleasure Bor of aversion
they're by Nature not acutely given to
melness and don't don't often experience
the pain of displeasure born of melness
but the five
faculties U manifest in them weakly and
because of that they only slowly come
into proximity of the D direction of the
influxes and then the pleasant practice
with swift Insight is when someone isn't
by Nature acutely given to the theats
and uh they do have the strong faculties
as well so because of that they swiftly
come into proximity of the destruction
of the influxes so so these are the four
kinds of
practice so we can start with a simple
question is it a matter of
choice whether your practice is Pleasant
or not because you often hear this idea
that especially when we talk about
know enduring pain h on the mental level
uh you know on on the right endurance
and not giv into UNH wholesome States
and and that often there's a certain um
displeasure associated with that because
you're preventing the Mind from having
things that it wants and so there's
often this idea
that unpleasant practices need to be
balanced out with Pleasant practices
from time to time because otherwise um
it's going to be too much which kind of
implies that yes Pleasant and un
Pleasant practice is a matter of choice
it's like based on the method that you
do or something like that um
so we can clearly see that that's not
yeah is it isn't a matter of choice the
degree to which you've been acting out
to Greed aversion delusion up until the
point of which you find yourself yeah
yeah because what the Baseline is
exactly because that's what's going to
determine um whether it's Pleasant or
not like you know um if you have a a dog
that's very used to just doing whatever
it wants and then you go for a walk with
it you know trying to make it go where
you want it to go it's not going to be
pleasant because it's going to be trying
to go everywhere else except where you
want it to go and um you know it's going
to be very strong and that's not going
to be a pleasant
walk so um
that's as simple as it gets so whereas
if you have a dog that is not is used to
being tame and is yeah as used to being
well trained when you go for a walk
it'll be very easy yeah exactly so
that's why well actually um the word
Suka and
Dua often is translated as as uh
pleasure and
displeasure but another accurate
translation for it would be
easy and
difficult so you could say it's easy
practice with uh slow results slow or
fast results or difficult practice with
slow or fast results yes but then it is
important to still keep in mind that
what is your choice is whether you
practice or not exactly yeah and what
the practice is and that it's the well
that what the practice is isn't a matter
of choice like taming the animal isn't a
matter of choice
but what what people would think is that
like putting a pause on their Taming of
the animal and doing something
completely different is also practice
and that's a pleasant practice Yeah like
you have a say yeah yeah but but what's
really happening there is at that moment
you're not
practicing when when like if you if you
stop feeling the
tension of the dog that's not tamed it's
because you're not holding the leash
anymore well or verse the dog might be
taking you oh yeah exactly yeah yeah one
of those two yeah
so um of course
it's for most people today
definitely because of the starting point
of of being used to a lot of pleasures
and inde dependencies and attachments it
is going to be difficult um so it
doesn't mean that you need to do it all
at once that you need to go from from
you know full uh Indulgence to to just
being completely secluded isolated from
everything and and you
know asceticism yeah just restrain
everything basically yeah uh you you can
do it
gradually so even if it takes you 5 10
years 15 years at least you're doing the
practice and you're not cheating
yourself into thinking that you know by
not doing the practice and just
distracting myself with whatever U
pleasures of of Oblivion that you're
that that's somehow contributing to The
Taming of the mind so another thing is
how would you know if your mind is is
a which kind of predisposition you have
is it something that that would be
obvious to you or is it something that
um needs to needs more kind
of acute to discernment to to
see well with these five faculties you
basically wouldn't really know until you
got the right view right of course but
uh when it comes to the passion aversion
and and modness if if you're how would
you know if you're acutely predisposed
to those defilements or not well uh take
the a precept seriously for example and
you'll find out and if that idea of
taking the eight precepts
seriously if if on the level of ideas of
those eight precepts you already have
you are already challenged and begin to
say did this can't be right or well this
is only for monks or right you notice
excuses coming up there yeah yeah uh
well then you are not on the route of
the pleasant practice basically yeah
yeah because
um you know when you read that it can
often sound like oh yeah strong passion
strong version so it it brings up this
image of like this ravenous kind of
crazy lust or something that somebody
might have butth you have to realize
that from your perspective all your
defilements always feel normal because
that's what you live with yes so so you
will never be able to to like um well
maybe if you've met other people and
then through conversation you realize
that you know for them it's easy and for
you it's not or something but uh if all
all you have is your own point of view
it's always going to feel normal it's
you're only going to start
realizing how strong it is as you said
when you start putting limits on uh what
the mind is allowed to do when you start
taking the presar yeah and also a notion
like normal is slippery ground to begin
with so you cannot take that as a
standard yeah uh so so that feeds into
the whole discussion of authenticity do
something for example because everybody
else is doing it or because it's
accepted in society and so on if that
becomes the standard you can already
forget understanding of Dharma that has
as its main characteristic that it goes
against the grain yeah and and one of
those things about nor normality quote
unquote is as we mentioned before the
the distinction between like practice
for months and practice for L but you
might think like it's normal for Lay
people to have some amount of lust
because you know they're lay people uh
but the thing is if you see the dhama as
the practice that's meant to lead to
your own Weare and you see craving as
against your own welfare then like you
wouldn't be saying like oh yeah it's
normal for me to have this amount of
cancer yeah so so
um and even late disciples and the sutas
they would come to the Buddha and they
would tell him you know I'm worried
because despite being a lay person
because it doesn't matter fundamentally
despite being a lay person I see that my
mind is frequently coming up with these
UNH wholesome States and you know I know
that that shouldn't happen and uh and so
they had that sense of Shame and sense
of of this is wrong which is one of the
faculties of of a no disciple even
though they were lay people so that's
that authenticity factor and uh you know
taking responsibility for your own mind and
responsibility for your own mind and
realizing that you know it's the
training is not you're not doing it
because the external code of being a
monk um sort of forces you to to take it
to this extent you're taking it to the
full extent because why would you want
to suffer
yes um so yeah and uh practically
um so yeah and uh practically
speaking you know given that the
starting point for most of us nowadays
is is very much in the opposite
direction of renunciation like
how often do you find someone who who
just by Nature keeps the
precepts even even Buddhists for that
matter somebody who you know they're not
being forced they're not
monks they just took on the eight
precepts and and they find it easy and
it's not um it's not trouble for them at
all yeah or just to have or or even one
step back to just even if they sometimes
slip up to still see that it is
worthwhile reestablishing themselves and
keeping that as a value yes with all the
books on Buddhism that have been
published since let's say the late 1960s
we're talking about thousands of books
that have flooded the West how many
books even make that
point yeah well I can say unfortunately
I've read hundreds of them but no it's
just at best it's
optional so that so from that point of
view the the introduction of Buddhism in
the vest has been somewhat of a disaster
yeah and and you can tell also that um
as we were saying before it's your mind
may not necessarily have uh you know
strong like like as I said before lust of like
like like as I said before lust of like
oh I just can't help I just need this it
might just be very simple excuses that
that that it comes up with and to kind
of like make you um
stop sooner and and uh if you don't stop you
sooner and and uh if you don't stop you
will realize you know as as it goes on
that it is actually intensifying and it
is really just an irrational pure
passion stop keeping the precepts
here yeah yeah so the mind is trying to
convince you to stop keeping the
precepts um so if you if you don't
listen to those like superficial
excuses and uh and you actually stay
with it over time you realize no no
actually it is just pure craving pure
passion pure desire that the mind like
that's why it's kind of like pre-
rational and so because the mind wants
to avoid the pain it comes up with these
excuses but because you don't see your
own mind uh you might then trust that oh
yeah it's you know I'm doing it because
I'm an a person or because of this is
because of that but really um the true
reason you're not admitting it so and I
think like it's exactly what the the Su
is pointing pointing to is like despite
the fact that you you keep the precept
you sense strength and so on like the
pleasure or the pain is not for you a
guideline to follow how do you feel is
not what is your is not a criteria to
follow basically and also like how fast
is the result is also not a criteria to
follow it's just keep doing it and and
also do you see that you are restraining
great div version in illusion because
there are often times where you know
when you have these whole Danga
practices and uh that people can become
very inspired by and uh that would be
generally regarded as like yeah
unpleasant practice or something but the
thing is you you would just adopt these
external observances you not clear about
how is it that this um actually
influences your G of and delusion you're
not even aware of that you may be doing
those practices with great adversion and
delusion on a different level of course
than than just the pure sensuality so um
it's it's neither how you feel nor how
quick it is nor any of this it's direct
seeing of Def filment and absence of Def
founds and that's why that suta that we
discussed the other in one of the
previous stuffs where they would have
said the the the standard that you
should go by is not the tradition is not
Authority is not even Reon your own
reasoning and logic it's what is
affected with greed or what is rooted in
non- greed uh what is Passion uh sorry
what is aversion what is non aversion
that should be your criteria for what is
uh beneficial and not beneficial uh
because and there are plenty of of this
the Buddha says it's the K suta yeah
yeah yeah there are plenty of sutas
where the where the Buddha says uh what
the majority regards as pleasant the
noble ones regard as unpleasant yeah
when the noble ones regard as uh
unpleasant the majority regard is
Pleasant M
so
um that uh that's how it's going to be
like the same practice the same name
giving up which is by the way where the
joy comes from in the sutas it's always
like the joy of renunciation the joy of
non sensuality yeah because that's the
thing there's this other suta which also
talks about Pleasant and unpleasant
practice and then it says pleasurable
practice it describes the forjas and
then unpleasant practice has to do with
these perceptions that the noble the
sideb can contemplate like U manful of
death uh perception of impermanence
attractiveness non Delight in the whole
world well exactly repulsiveness of food
and and so on so but then the pleasant
practice being the Jana that is again
not the result of some technique that
you have received but rather fully the
result of virt and restraint yeah
because uh there's there's one discour
where the Buddha before his enlightment
he asked
himself essentially why isn't why is it
that even though I see the benefit of
renunciation my my practice isn't
Pleasant that's one way you could
paraphrase what he said like why is it
that the mind doesn't leap at
renunciation it doesn't feel confident
it doesn't feel kind of re um relieved
by it mhm and and he realized oh it's
because I haven't sufficiently seen the
danger in sensuality and then once that
he saw that
sufficiently then the The Joy arose and
he basically entered the first J because
it's that same giving up that for you is
unpleasant initially um that you know
like just
imagine um is
it if
something that you really want gets
taken away from
you that's obviously unpleasant MH but
if something that you
saw was harmful was like a like um like
a like a dart like an arrow that was
deeply dug digging into your leg or
something and then it gets taken away
would you be sad because it was taken
away no you would be that would be the
right type of Joy um so it's and and
always in the suas the the joy is
described as um the joy of having
abandoned un wholesome Stakes mhm it's
not just the the joy of of thinking nice
thoughts or something um now of
course um pleasure Pleasant feelings
will arise sometimes whether you like it
or not so we're not saying that that you
need to like destroy every Pleasant
feeling that
arises uh but the Buddha made this
distinction between pleasure that
pleasure that should be cultivated yes
and pleasure that shouldn't be
cultivated even if it arises yeah so
there's the pleasure bound up with
sensuality and there's the pleasure of
renunciation yeah so both are a pleasure
but they are in opposite directions yeah
and and like we said like the pleasure
of sensuality where as long as you have
five senses it will be there you will
not be seeking it but some extent of it
will be there even just because you have
to eat every day so so um but you
realize as the Buddha said that pleasure
is dangerous should not be like
intentionally sought after and made much
of
so that's that's the point you will have
you will have pleasant feelings uh of
the wrong kind um whether you like it or
not but what the pleasant feelings that
should be practiced and should be made a
vehicle are the pleasant feelings that
uh are would arise in regard to the same
thing that for you right now might be
very painful and a
pleasant yeah and this is why faith is
also the first of these faculties that
it mentioned in this discourse and
that's precisely this point so what you
regard as pleasurable now is actually
painful so you need to go through the
renunciation in order to gain let's say
the wholesome pleasure but without
having faith that such a wholesome
pleasure is possible you never give up
the other one because it's the only one
you know yeah from the starting point
yeah yeah so
so then that lack of faith precisely
actually would would be the same thing
that would uh make you impatient and
would make you want to get the pleasure
that you can get now because you don't
want to actually like fix the
illness which you know requires taking
this medicine that might be quite
bitter uh you want to just stop feeling
the pain of the treatment at all costs
and then you take another medicine that
kind of um removes the side effects of this
of um removes the side effects of this
good medicine but also removes the
actual good effect as well yeah so then
it cancels it out and that's really what
that joyful practice quote unquote um uh
that people would think is a matter of
choice or matter of some technique that
you do or something that's what it's
really doing it's canceling the practice
it's quite a funny things because if it
was a matter of choice I could not
imagine the Buddha like mentioning
anything else than a fast and a pleasant
practice because yeah it would be know
your practice should be fast and quick
abon everything else but it's not what
he said exactly yeah yeah and and you
have multiple I
mean quite explicitly it says um because
this neana cannot be attained without
great perseverance
effort diligence um endurance
patience that you have so many verses
saying that and and from many monks and
from the Buddha himself MH so if it were
a matter of just something easy that
that you know from the very start is
just going to be sweet and and like it's
it's precisely because that direction of
nibana is against the grain as we said
that's why beings are
naturally by going the opposite
direction if the if the dhama if if
renunciation if um giving up if nibana
if nonidentification were
pleasant everyone would naturally be
they would have it by now yeah no and
they would they would be inclining
towards neana whether they hear the Dum
or not everyone would be like a pikaa or
something eventually
um so but it's not so as said if beings
don't hear the dhama the majority of
them they just yeah they go down yeah
because that's what what is that's what
feels natural that's what feels
easy from where you
stand yeah and also regarding what you
say like a bit earlier um about the
Danga practice
like that's way more easy to assume that
doing this certain things like whatever
it is like I don't know going naked in
the forest or whatever you want to do um
that's way more easy than to sit in your
room alone and not not knowing what you
you're supposed to do yeah like this
kind of doubt is way more unpleasant to
bear and that require the patience and
endurance that we mentioning before we
like assuming that already know the
practice that is just going in the
forest naked that doesn't require any
patience and endurance because you seem
you already know so it's not during
control yeah exactly yeah yeah it's that
safety of um having something that I can just
of um having something that I can just
stick to and then magically the results
will come and it's exactly the same as
any Cal like craving B because it's
exactly the same attitude like when I
want to smoke a cigarette is because I
believe that this cigarettes will fix my
problem later the same thing is as the Buddha
later the same thing is as the Buddha
said you're seeking after what requires
time like when he said the principle of
like when he said the principle of
sensuality is seeking after things that
require time yes V the dama is always
Timeless yeah so to yeah so to not give
in to pressure is immediate yeah whereas
to follow your desires always involves
some effort but in the beginning it will
not look like that yeah but that's not
the difficulty but I meant even even
here of course you have the the crude
sensuality and stuff but even with this
it's it's exactly the same principle
with tang yeah yeah like just the blind
hope that I just do this and sometime
later something will happen you're not
seeing the pressure now and by the way
like we talk about Danga like as kind of
crazy practice but just like going
sitting alone in front of a in front of
a wall and following your breathing for
an hour focusing techniques yeah that's
actually is the same principle there
Adana don't move for an hour don't move
for three hours yeah even if your leg
hurts don't don't don't move at all
that's the same
things yeah so so
that is
easier than
um you know the uncertainty of having to
clarify your views as you said recognize
what is actually wholesome like am I
actually C clear about that uh
so that in itself is is one of the most
uh unpleasant elements of the practice
it's not just uh cuz sure there's the
the addiction to sensuality there's that
but even once you overcome that there's
still that doubt you still have doubt
about you know the practice what you
should do the mind trying to find any
Avenue it can to to kind of
like push you astray and distract
yourself from what actually matters
so yeah it's it's uh
until you not on your own ownn terms on terms
you not on your own ownn terms on terms
of you having actually tamed the mind
you overcome the five hindrances which
include doubt practice has to be going against
doubt practice has to be going against
grain has to be
unpleasant to begin with yeah because it
could then turn out that you find
yourself in a situation where it's not
unpleasant and and
then then you don't also have to
then go out of your way
to get anxious about the fact that it's
not unpleasant yeah can we say that the
unpleasantness is
um is in regard to the fact that I
decide to stop regarding my feeling as a
criteria to live my life and that
stopping to like relate my feeling it
that way is what is unpleasant can we
say that so you're saying the fact the thing
that so you're saying the fact the thing
that's un Pleasant is that you no longer
take feelings as a Criterion for your
actions yeah yeah exactly is it what
what can be regarded as broadly speaking
Yeah because that would Encompass more
than just the um obvious uh giving up of
like sure you start keeping the precepts
but are you actually no no longer longer
taking feelings as a criteria because
many people keep the precepts uh just
out of many wrong views and and doing
many wrong practices on top of it that
are still fundamentally based on making
themselves feel better as soon as
possible overlooking what is actually great
overlooking what is actually great
diversion and delusion am I acting out
of it have I actually understood that or
yeah am I still assuming that what is
wholesome is what feels good
H so yeah fundamentally um
realizing that you can no longer rely on
your feelings as a
guideline that would be like an
unpleasant recognition to begin with and
keeping that in mind would sort of um
filter out a lot of the wrong avenues
that you might you might go into but
then you want to also not um also want
to actually do that like not take
feelings as a criteria because a lot of
people that can then go in the opposite
direction and say I have to always be
feeling pain and torment and suffering
which is again I wonderly taking feeling
as a measure yeah exactly so so that's
how you know you would Drift from the
middle way you're too far into
Indulgence so you just kick back to the
complete opposite and um that's that's
that's pretty much the same thing like
you're still being driven by the
impulses of your mind it's not you
controlling your mind and you're not
teaching the Mind anything because
you're not
allowing like the the animal
to learn when it's making a mistake if
you're if you're punishing it without it
making mistake first it has to make the
mistake in order like in order for it to
learn what mistake is you're just saying
existing is wrong or yeah yeah you
should be feeling pain now even though
it's just you know innocently just um
yeah you know breathing or sitting there
or doing something which isn't mistaken
yeah you're not teaching it anything it
has it has to make a mistake and then
then you punish it yeah so that's going
back to what we said you you you're not
really thinking in terms of what is
wholesome and wholesome you're not
teaching your mind you're not developing
understanding yeah so that's why um like
discernment fundamentally bows down to
that it's not um as we I think we've
mentioned that before it's not a these
these mystical perceptions of of
emptiness or something it's do you
actually know what is wholesome and un
wholesome can you know for sure that the
intentions that you're cultivating now
lead to niana or away from it yeah and
that has to be your criteria for for um
the practice and then you will get to
see down the line that um you know in
line with the formable truths and
everything the only reason why you were
finding restraint renunciation giving up
unpleasant uh it wasn't by accident
actually you were responsible even for
that pain because craving is the root of
suffering and craving is always if there
is suffering there has to be craving
presently at the same time time so it's
not really even because of like the past
things that you did um you could say the
past things that you did have increased
your ignorance because of which you don't see
ignorance because of which you don't see
craving and because of which you suffer
now no but uh if you if you were to
recognize actually you you you were to
actually make that distinction with
discernment like picking things apart
and seeing actually um uh unpleasant
feeling is one thing craving is another
then uh there would be no ground for
suffering so regardless of what has
happened in the past exactly so the B is
responsible for the intensity of the
feelings that that you now are either
equation for or against that is still
the result of Kama which is the let's
say the results in time yeah but now the
situation that you are confronted with
either you understand craving is the
origin of suffering or not and that has
nothing to do with the intensity of the
the experience to discernment
encompasses all of that yeah so so uh
it's said in that way
because obviously like ultimately it's
that Timeless principle abandoning
craving leads to abandoning suffering
immediately but you won't start out
seeing craving so so what will happen is
you will have these intense feelings
coming up throughout your practice and
uh it will be unle because you don't see
craving but uh it is through that
practice that you are removing the
obstacles for seeing craving asoen of
suffering yeah yeah